Preliminary Inventory to the Communist Party of South Africa Issuances, 1937-1943
Hoover Institution Archives
Communist Party of South Africa Issuances,
1937-1943
XX051
Communist Party of South Africa
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Pamphlets and leaflets, relating to political conditions, race relations, and the labor movement in South Africa, and to the South African role in World War II. Includes some material issued by other leftist South African organizations.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Communism.; Communism--South Africa.; Trade-unions--South Africa.; World War, 1939-1945.; South Africa--Politics and government.; South Africa--Race relations.; World War, 1939-1945--South Africa.; South Africa.; Africa.
Container List
- Blackshirts! Greyshirts! Hunger! Slavery! Oppresion and War!, pamphlet (10 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The National Liberation League of South Africa, Municipal By-Election, Ward 7, 1 page flyer
- South African Friends of the Soviet Union, 4 flyers
- 24 Wonderlike Jare, 'n Kort Geskiedenis van die Sowjet-Unie, pamphlet (18 p.)
- Time to Wake Up Mister! a Guardian, pamphlet (17 p.)
- The Guardian flyer (advertising for subscriptions)
- General Smuts says: 'Communism is a Local Product'. General Smuts is Right, George Sacks lecture announcement
- The National Question Solved, Friends of the Soviet Union, pamphlet (10 p.)
- Peoples Theatre Pretoria presents Stay Down Miner by Montagu Slater, program, (8 p.)
- Die Kommuniste-Manifes deur Karl Marx en Friedrich Engels, Werkersparty van Suid-Afrika, pamphlet (27 p.)
- Die Afrikaner en Britse Imperialisme, Franz Boshoff, pamphlet (12 p.)
- Finland: The Facts about Russia's Motive: Finnish History: The Strategy of the War, The Guardian, pamphlet (7 p.)
- The Munich Swindle, The Guardian, pamphlet (5 p.)
- What is Russia Driving At? announcement of a meeting in Capetown, September 1, 1939, Friends of the Soviet Union, (2 p.)
- Whither South Africa Whither? The National Peoples' Movement, flyer
- Tom Mann Memorial Meeting, April 1, 1941, program
- The National Peoples' Movement, statement of purpose and background
- All Aid to the U.S.S.R., Donald M. Molteno, Guardian pamphlet, (8 p.)
- The Guardian, rate card
- A Call to the Citizens of South Africa - Awake from the Dream, Democratic League of South Africa, flyer
- Who Caused the Riots? Mass Assaults on Non-Europeans. Non-European United Front of S.A., flyer
- Race Contacts Committee, C.T., Public Meeting of Citizens, announcements, April 2, 1941
- We Want to Live! South African Railway & Harbour Workers Union, pamphlet (8 p.)
- Memorandum on the General Council of the National Liberation League of S.A., National Liberation League of South Africa, pamphlet (5 p.)
- Fascism Mean War! What Blackshirts Stand For, South African Anti-Fascist Movement, Johannesburg, flyer
- Socialism - The Way Out, Guardian supplement No. 4, October 24, 1940, (8 p.)
- What We Want to Know, The National Peoples Movement, Johannesburg, flyer
- Truth on Finland, Ivor Montagu, Guardian supplement No. 1, February 16, 1940, (8 p.)
- Molteno, Donald, M.P. & others, letter announcing the formation of a Civil Liberties Council in Cape Town, May 29, 1941
- Soviet Exhibition - Pictures, Facts & Figures About Our Ally, Friends of the Soviet Union, pamphlet (5 p.)
- Workers Conference Against Segregation, March 31, 1941, Coordinating Committee of Trade Unions and Non-European Organisations, flyer
- Paarl Strike - Food Bosses pay Starvation Wages, meeting announcement, Food and Canning Workers Union, Cape Town, flyer
- Security in a Changing World? Peoples College and Peoples Club, flyer (2 p.)
- May Day Mass Demonstration & Concert, Cape Town, announcement, May 1, 1942, (4 p.)
- May Day 1941 - Workers Rally, United May Day Committee, flyer (2 p.)
- Here Friend - Poems, Peter Abrahams, pamphlet, 1941, (12 pages)
- List of pamphlets, periodicals, etc., issued by the Communist Party and leftist organizations of South Africa, (2 p.) (Folder 2)
- Vereeniging - Who is to Blame? pamphlet, Communist Party of South Africa, (11 p.)
- They Marched to Victory! The Story of the Alexandra Bus Boycott, Communist Party Pamphlet, (13 p.)
- What is Behind the 'Anti-Communist' Campaign? Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (5 p.)
- The Untold Story of South Africa, Kent Hunter, pamphlet (5 p.)
- Japan - Friend or Foe? Moses K. Kotane, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (6 p.)
- 10,000,000 For Freedom, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (8 p.)
- Seven Words - Common Ownership of the Means of Production, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (10 p.)
- Programme for Victory - Workers, Men and Women of South Africa! Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (3 p.)
- Soviet Russia - Liberator of the Peoples, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (7 p.)
- The Truth About the Red Army, Johannesburg Communist Party, pamphlet (9 p.)
- Stand By the Soviet Union, George Heard, South African Friends of the Soviet Union, pamphlet (8 p.)
- They Fight for Trade Union Rights! Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (5 p.)
- Peoples Pageant - Souvenir Programme, celebrating the 24th anniversary of the Russian Revolution, Cape District Committee of the Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (20 p.)
- South Africans Awake! Our Country is in Danger! Communist Party of South Africa, flyer (4 p.)
- Meet the Communists, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (13 p.)
- Keep Calm - Don't Panic - A Criticism of Durban C.P.S. and a Plan for Action, Durban District Committee of the Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (19 p.)
- Unite Against Segregation! Communist Condemn the C.A.C., Communist Party of South Africa, flyer (2 p.)
- Now We Can Answer the Question: What Is Capitalism? George Sacks, Cape District Committee of the Communist Party, flyer (2 p.)
- New Homes for Old! Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (10 p.)
- Advance, Organ of Berea-Yeoville Branch, S.A. Labour Party
  - No. 2, February 1940, (11 p.)
  - No. 3, April 1940, (14 p.)
- Youth, Official Organ of the Labour League of Youth of S. Africa, February 1939, pamphlet (8 p.)
- A Call to Action! Workers and People of South Africa... Smash Fascism Now! October 13, 1941, Communist Party of South Africa, flyer (2 p.)
- 6 Point Communist Programme, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (16 p.)
- Organise a People's Front in South Africa, September 1936, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (12 p.)
- Must We Fight, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (17 p.)
- Protect Cape Town!, (1942?) Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (9 p.)
- The Second Front Now! D.P.C. of the Communist Party of South Africa, (1942?), pamphlet (3 p.)
- Wipe Fascism off the Face of the Earth! Smash Hitler Now... Johannesburg District Communist Party, pamphlet (3 p.)
- A New Year's Message for South Africa 1941, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (7 p.)
- A New Year's Message to South Africa for 1942, Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (7 p.)
- Hampering the War Effort, Pretoria District of the Communist Party of South Africa, pamphlet (4 p.)